Finding Aid for School of Public Health (University of Michigan) Records 1909-2015 (bulk 1941-2006).
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Institutes and Inservice Courses, 1942-1957
  - 1952
    - Citizen's Public Health Conference (Box 8)
    - Community Planning Health Services (Box 8)
    - Noise (Box 8)
  - 1953
    - Expert and Technical Testimony (Box 8)
    - Health Conference for Public Officials (Box 8)
    - Home Accident Prevention (Box 8)
  - 1954
    - Instrumentation for Industrial Hygiene (Box 8)
    - Nursing Care for the Aged (Box 8)
  - 1955
    - Citizen's Public Health Conference (Box 8)
    - Evaluation in Public Health (Box 8)
  - 1956
    - Health Conference for Public Officials (Box 8)
    - Radioactive Wastes (Box 8)
  - 1957
    - Administration in Local Health Departments (Box 8)
- Program in Public Health Nursing, 1909-1977
  The records of the Program in Public Health Nursing series span the years 1909-1977, but the bulk of the collection relates to the years 1941-1977 when the School of Public Health offered a graduate degree in public health nursing. This series consists of two linear feet of materials. Filed at the beginning of this series is a volume titled, "A Brief History of Public Health Nursing Education at the University of Michigan, 1919-1930," by Ruth Bishop, and one folder of miscellaneous historical notes and correspondence, 1909-1950. The rest of the records are arranged alphabetically by topic. Significant topics include: accreditation reports, 1956 and 1975; annual reports, 1961-1977; faculty minutes, 1941-1973; and reviews of the program, 1960 and 1968.
  - Historical Material
    - "A Brief History of Public Health Nursing Education at the University of Michigan, 1919-1930," by Ruth Bishop (Box 9)
    - Notes and Memoranda, 1909-1950 (Box 9)
  - Accreditation Reports, 1956; 1975 (Box 9)
  - Advisory Committee, 1941-1977; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Annual Reports, 1961-1977; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Cooperative Education Project, 1959-1966 (Box 9)
  - Emily G. Sargent Award (Box 9)
  - Faculty Minutes, 1947-1973; 6 folders (Box 9)
  - Field Experience Reports, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Field Work, 6 folders (Box 9)
  - Grant Projects, circa 1975-1977 (Box 10)
    - Community Health Masters Program, 1976-1977; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Planning Graduate Education in PHN, 1977 (Box 10)
    - Teaching Nursing Aspects of Medical Care Administration (Box 10)
  - Kellogg Foundation, 1936-1946; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - NOPHN Collegiate Council Work Conference, 1951 (Box 10)
  - Review of School, 1960; 1968 (Box 10)
  - Self-Survey of Guides for PHN Service, 1953 (Box 10)
  - Seminar Paper Topics, 1944-1946 (Box 10)
  - Students Granted Degrees, 1925-1977 (Box 10)
  - Student Papers
    - Phelan, Katherine, "Opinions of PHN Graduates Receiving the MPH Degree from the University of Michigan, 1958-1962, About the Field Course in PHN Supervision and Administration", 1963 (Box 10)
    - Beckman, Sylvia, "Faculty-Student Ratio for Supervision of Students in PHN Field Experience in Baccalaureate Programs in Which Faculty Assume Full Responsibility for Faculty Instruction,", 1964 (Box 10)
  - Termination of Undergraduate Program, 1960-1961 (Box 10)
  - Use of Practical Nurse Students in Home Care of Cancer Patients, 1951 (Box 10)
  - Workshops, 1944-1971
    - Industrial Health Nursing, 1954; 1966 (Box 10)
    - PHN in Northern Michigan, 1952 (Box 10)
    - School Nurses, 1948-1953 (Box 10)
    - Supervising Nurses/Field Teachers, 1944-1971; 4 folders (Box 10)
  - Photographs (Box 10)
- Association of Schools of Public Health, 1941-2002
  Included within the School of Public Health collection are the records of the Association of Schools of Public Health (ASPH), 1941-2002. The ASPH is the professional organization and accrediting body for public health schools in the United States. The records of ASPH are arranged in several subseries based on the chronological span represented in various accessions which have been received by library.
  - Files, 1941-1959; 12 folders
    The 1941-1959 subseries is organized into University of Michigan Correspondence, 1941-1959; Minutes, 1941-1961; General Correspondence, 1946-1957; Legislation File, 1948-1959; Accreditation Reports, 1948-1949; and Accreditation Study, 1953. The University of Michigan Correspondence file belongs, in one sense, in Dean Vaughan's Topical Files. It consists of letters between Vaughan and the officers of the association. The rest of the ASPH material is more properly the archives of the organization which, for some reason, were deposited with the School of Public Health. The General Correspondence consists of letters between ASPH officers and the deans of other public health schools, government officials, and other health professionals. The Legislation Files include material on several Congressional bills designed to provide support for public health education. These files contain some interesting information on the relationship between the public health movement and the established medical profession as represented by the American Medical Association. The Accreditation Reports are summary reports on the programs of what were then the ten graduate schools of public health in the United States.
    - Correspondence (University of Michigan), 1941-1959; 12 folders (Box 11)
    - Minutes, 1941-1961; 5 folders (Box 11)
    - General Correspondence, 1946-1951; 3 folders (Box 11)
    - General Correspondence, 1952-1957; 4 folders (Box 12)
    - Legislation File, 1948-1959; 7 folders (Box 12)
    - Accreditation Reports, 1948-1949 (Box 12)
    - Accreditation Study, 1953 (Box 12)
    - Wegman Correspondence/Testimony, 1964 (Box 12)
  - Files, 1973-1983
    The Association of Schools of Public Health, 1972-1983 subseries comprises two linear feet and continue the documentation of this professional organization and accrediting body of the United States Public Health Service (see also boxes 11 and 12). The ASPH material in the 1989 accession is not as University of Michigan-oriented but is retained with the collection due to Remington's active involvement in shaping ASPH policy. Of special note are the "Friday Letters" which weekly document the position of the ASPH on issues, legislation, and actions needed for the period from 1977 to 1984. The other files dealing with external issues is the PBB Study; these materials run 0.6 linear feet in Box 48 and document the school's efforts to establish via epidemiological and biological evidence the far reaching implications of polybrominated biphenyls on human health.
    - Annual Meetings, 1979-1982
      - New Orleans, April 1979 (Box 39)
      - Atlanta, August 1979 (Box 39)
      - New York, November 1979 (Box 39)
      - Detroit, October 1980 (Box 39)
      - Washington, D.C., March 1981 (Box 39)
      - Birmingham, AL, April 1982; 2 folders (Box 39)
      - Montreal, November 1982 (Box 39)
    - Committees, 1978-1982
      - Accreditation, 1981-1982 (Box 39)
      - Executive, 1978-1979; 2 folders (Box 39)
      - Legislative, 1981-1982; 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1983
      - Milbank Memorial Fund Commission, 1975-1977 (Box 39)
      - General, 1978-1979; 2 folders (Box 39)
      - Gemell, Michael (Executive Director), 1978-1979 (Box 39)
      - Michael, J. M. (President), 1978-1979 (Box 39)
      - Perlman, Eva Jakso (includes list of "star graduates"), 1978-1979 (Box 39)
      - General, 1980 (Box 39)
      - Gemell, Michael (Executive Director), 1980 (Box 39)
      - General, 1981 (Box 39)
      - General, 1982 (Box 39)
      - General, 1983 (Box 39)
  - Files, 1975-1984
    The Association of Schools of Public Health materials comprise two linear feet and continue the documentation of this professional organization and accrediting body of the United States Public Health Service. The ASPH material in the 1989 accession is not as University of Michigan-oriented but is retained with the collection due to Remington's active involvement in shaping ASPH policy. Of special note are the "Friday Letters" which weekly document the position of the ASPH on issues, legislation, and actions needed for the period from 1977 to 1984.
    - Annual Meetings, 1979-1982
      - New Orleans, April 1979 (Box 39)
      - Atlanta, August 1979 (Box 39)
      - New York, November 1979 (Box 39)
      - Detroit, October 1980 (Box 39)
      - Washington, D.C., March 1981 (Box 39)
      - Birmingham, AL, April 1982; 2 folders (Box 39)
      - Montreal, November 1982 (Box 39)
    - Committees, 1978-1982
      - Accreditation, 1981-1982 (Box 39)
      - Executive, 1978-1979; 2 folders (Box 39)
      - Legislative, 1981-1982; 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1983
      - Milbank Memorial Fund Commission, 1975-1977 (Box 39)
      - General, 1978-1979; 2 folders (Box 39)
      - Gemell, Michael (Executive Director), 1978-1979 (Box 39)
      - Michael, J. M. (President), 1978-1979 (Box 39)
      - Perlman, Eva Jakso, 1978-1979 (Box 39)
        (includes list of "star graduates")
      - General, 1980 (Box 39)
      - Gemell, Michael (Executive Director), 1980 (Box 39)
      - General, 1981 (Box 39)
      - General, 1982 (Box 39)
      - General, 1983 (Box 39)
    - "Friday Letters,", 1978-1984; 21 folders (Box 40)
  - Files, 1984-1992
    The Association of Schools of Public Health (ASPH), 1984-1992 subseries, 2.6 linear feet, continues where the previous accession ended. The records document interaction with this organization which works to advance public health education, compile data on public health manpower, and serve as a liaison between public health schools, government agencies and other organizations. These functions are illustrated in the records which include annual meeting files, data reports, and correspondence with other deans and the ASPH executive director. The records also include the weekly "Friday Letters" briefs, 1985-1991.
    - Annual Meetings
      - Charleston, SC, April 1984 (Box 49)
      - Anaheim, CA, November 1984 (Box 49)
      - San Juan, PR, March 1985 (Box 49)
      - Washington, D.C., November 1985 (Box 49)
      - Washington, D.C., April 1988 (Box 49)
      - Washington, D.C., April 1989 (Box 49)
      - Chicago, IL, October 1989 (Box 49)
      - Washington, D.C., April 1990 (Box 49)
      - Washington, D.C., March 1991 (Box 49)
      - Washington, D.C., March 1992 (Box 49)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1984-1990; 6 folders (Box 49)
      - Gemell, Michael (Executive Director), 1984-1991; 6 folders (Box 49)
    - Reports
      - "Data Report on Applicants, Students, Graduates and Expenditures 1983-84 with Trends Analysis for 1974-75 through 1983-84,", 1985 (Box 49)
      - "Data Report on Applicants, Students, Graduates and Expenditures 1985-86 with Trends Analysis for 1974-75 through 1985-86,", 1987 (Box 49)
      - "Professional Development Programs Sponsored by Accredited U.S. Schools of Public Health"
        - Part I: Non-Traditional Degree and Credential/Certificate Programs, 1989 (Box 49)
        - Part II: Continuing Education Programs, 1989 (Box 49)
        - Part III A: Applicants, Students, and Graduates of Non-Traditional Degree and Credential/Certificate Programs, 1989 (Box 49)
        - Part III B: Students in Continuing Education Programs, 1989 (Box 49)
    - "Friday Letters,"
      - 1985-1989, 5 folders (Box 50)
      - 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 51)
  - Files, 1984-2002
    - Committees
      - Education Committee
        - General (Box 83)
          [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2025 ]
        - 2000 (Box 83)
      - Executive Committee
        - Executive Committee Meetings
          - January 11, 2000 (Box 83)
          - March 7, 2000 (Box 83)
          - February 1 2001 (Box 83)
          - March 12, 2001 (Box 83)
        - General (Box 83)
      - Task Force on Image of Public Health, 1997-1998 (Box 83)
    - Competencies and Accreditation
      - Accreditation Initiative (Box 83)
      - Competencies Project, 2 folders (Box 83)
      - Core Competencies, 2000 (Box 83)
      - Other Schools of Public Health (Box 83)
      - Preview of Association of Schools of Public Health Delphi Process Comments, Round 1, 2002 (Box 84)
      - Subcommittee on Competencies, 2001 (Box 84)
    - Correspondence
      - Gemmel, Mike
        - 1992 (Box 84)
        - 1993 (Box 84)
        - 1998 (Box 84)
        - 1999 (Box 84)
      - General, 1992-2000; 9 folders (Box 84)
    - General
      - Advisor's Guide to Public Health, undated (Box 84)
      - Association of Schools of Public Health/ Center for Disease Control Cooperative Agreement, 1984-1987 (Box 84)
      - Association of Schools of Public Health, Director/President, 1999-2001; 2 folders (Box 84)
      - Association of Schools of Public Health, Miscellaneous, 2001 (Box 84)
      - The Future of Public Health, 1988-1997 (Box 85)
      - Behavioral Science Interests, 1997-2000 (Box 85)
      - Distance Education in Public Health, 1995 (Box 85)
      - National Institutes of Health, Connections/Strategies, 1999-2001 (Box 85)
    - Meetings
      - Association of Schools of Public Health Deans' Retreats
        - April 21-23, 1993 (Box 85)
        - October 25-27, 1993 (Box 85)
        - July 27-30, 1994 (Box 85)
        - October 30-November 3, 1994 (Box 85)
        - July 12-15, 1995 (Box 85)
        - October 28-31, 1995 (Box 85)
        - July 24-27, 1996 (Box 85)
        - July 23-26, 1997 (Box 85)
        - July 22-25, 1998 (Box 85)
        - November 14-17, 1998 (Box 85)
        - July 22-24, 1999 (Box 85)
        - July 25-28, 2001 (Box 86)
      - Association of Schools of Public Health, Legislative Conference
        - April 13-14, 1994 (Box 86)
        - March 15-16, 1995 (Box 86)
        - March 13-14, 1996 (Box 86)
        - March 12-13, 1997 (Box 86)
        - March 11-12, 1998 (Box 86)
      - General
        - Community-Based Public Health Network Meeting, June 22, 1994 (Box 86)
        - Meeting of Region V Health Administrators, September 12, 1997 (Box 86)
        - Distance Education in Public Health, ASPH Annual Dean's Meeting, November, 14-17, 1998 (Box 86)
        - Meeting with Dr. Harlan, October 22, 1999 (Box 86)
        - WHO Conference on Women's Health, April 5-7, 2000 (Box 86)
        - Association of Schools of Public Health/ Center for Disease Control Meeting, March 12-13, 2001 (Box 86)
        - Association of Schools of Public Health Annual Meetings (Box 86)
    - Publications
      - Friday Letters
        - 1992-1993, 2 folders (Box 86)
        - 1994-2000, 7 folders (Box 87)
      - General
        - Association of Schools of Public Health Annual Report on Student Applications, Expenditures, etc. (Box 88)
          - 1996 (Box 88)
          - 1998 (Box 88)
        - Demonstrating Excellence in Public Health Practice, 1999 (Box 88)
        - Challenges and Opportunities in Understanding the Complexity of Living Systems, 1999 (Box 88)
        - Practice-Based Scholarship, 1999 (Box 88)
        - Weist, Liz, "Mastering the New Public Health", 2000 (Box 88)
- Dean Myron E. Wegman, 1958-1973
  The Dean Myron E. Wegman (1958-1973) series comprises twelve linear feet in boxes 13-24 and consists of annual reports, correspondence, memoranda, minutes and reports, and photographs. These materials are arranged in annual files just as they were in the office of creation. Beyond conforming to this annual file scheme there has been considerable rearrangement during processing. Within annual files in the original order, materials were arranged alphabetically according to the geographic point of origin or destination of the correspondence. As this filing system seemed awkward at best, the materials have been rearranged in six subseries: Administration (School of Public Health), American Public Health Association (APHA), Committees, Correspondence, Departments/Divisions, and Programs.
  The materials dealing most immediately with the school's administration and teaching (Administration, Committees, Departments/Divisions, and Programs) have been disturbed least in the course of processing. These materials provide insight to how the school handled questions of power and change during years of growth in terms of physical size, breadth of research, and the number of students and faculty. Unlike the spotty coverage in the Vaughan years, the Committees run is quite complete, if circumspect. The Departments/Divisions describe the growing complexity of the School; the subseries can be viewed as an extension of the Faculty Correspondence subseries of the Dean Henry F. Vaughan series.
  The materials which do not immediately relate to the school (American Public Health Association (APHA) and Correspondence subseries) have been significantly rearranged during processing. The APHA materials have been removed from the larger run of correspondence (where they had been filed under "N" for New York and "D" for Washington, D.C.) and left to stand alone as a subseries. The ASPH materials reflect the growing professionalization of public health and the increasing importance of education in securing professional status. The Correspondence subseries has been completely rearranged within each annual file, moved from its original geographic order to a rough chronology based on month of creation. A final note on records in this group concerns conservation; evidently the school's storage area leaked, as many of the files were water damaged. The Bentley Library also holds Myron Wegman's personal papers.
  - Annual Files, 1960-1961
    - Administration (Box 13)
      - Annual Reports, 1959-1961 (Box 13)
      - Peace Corps (Wegman's work with), 1961 (Box 13)
    - American Public Health Association
      - Annual Meeting (Detroit), 1961 (Box 13)
      - Committee on Professional Education, 1958-1961 (Box 13)
      - Editorial Board, 1960-1961 (Box 13)
    - Committees
      - Advisory Committee on Promotion, 1959-1960 (Box 13)
      - Assembly, 1960-1961 (Box 13)
      - Executive, 1959-1961 (Box 13)
      - Faculty Meetings, 1960-1961 (Box 13)
      - Instruction, 1960-1961 (Box 13)
      - Library, 1958-1961 (Box 13)
      - Search for Chairman, 1960 (Box 13)
    - Correspondence
      - 1960-1961, 6 folders (Box 13)
    - Departments/Divisions
      - Biostatistics (F. Moore), 1960-1961 (Box 13)
      - Community Health (V. Getting), 1960-1961; 2 folders (Box 13)
      - Environmental Health, 1961 (Box 13)
      - Epidemiology (T. Francis), 1960-1961
        - Tecumseh Study, 1960-1961 (Box 13)
      - Health Development (K. Easlick, M. Rugen, D. Smith), 1960-1961; 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Industrial Health, 1960-1961 (Box 13)
  - Annual Files, 1962-1963
    - Administration
      - General, 1962-1963 (Box 13)
      - Annual Reports, 1961-1962 (Box 13)
      - Library, 1962-1963 (Box 13)
      - Memoranda (department heads), 1962-1963 (Box 13)
      - Memoranda (faculty), 1962-1963 (Box 13)
      - Students, 1962-1963 (Box 13)
    - American Public Health Association
      - Annual Meeting (Miami), 1962 (Box 13)
      - Committee on Professional Education, 1962 (Box 13)
      - Editorial Board, 1962-1963 (Box 13)
    - Committees
      - Admissions, 1962-1963 (Box 14)
      - Advisory Committee on Promotions, 1960-1963 (Box 14)
      - Assembly, 1961-1963 (Box 14)
      - Continued Education and Community Relations, 1958-1963 (Box 14)
      - Executive, 1962-1963 (Box 14)
      - Faculty Meetings, 1962-1963 (Box 14)
      - Instruction, 1962-1964 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence
      - 1962-1963, 8 folders (Box 14)
    - Departments/Divisions
      - Biostatistics (F. Moore), 1962-1963 (Box 14)
      - Bureau of Public Health Economics (S. Axelrod), 1962-1963 (Box 14)
      - Community Health (V. Getting), 1962-1963; 2 folders
        - Public Health Nursing (McNeil), 1962-1963 (Box 14)
      - Environmental Health (C. Velz), 1962-1963 (Box 14)
      - Epidemiology (T. Francis), 1962-1963
        - Center for Research on Diseases of the Heart (nee Tecumseh Study), 1962-1963 (Box 14)
      - Health Development (K. Easlick, J. Eliot, M. Rugen, D. Smith), 1962-1963; 5 folders (Box 14)
      - Industrial Health (H. Magnuson), 1962-1963 (Box 14)
  - Annual Files, 1964-1965
    - Administration
      - General, 1964-1965 (Box 14)
      - Annual Reports, 1963-1964 (Box 14)
      - Memoranda (department heads), 1964-1965 (Box 14)
      - Memoranda (faculty), 1964-1965 (Box 14)
      - Population Planning Course (Ford Grant), 1964-1965 (Box 14)
      - Request for Proposal, W. K. Kellogg Foundation, 1964 (Box 14)
      - Students, 1964-1965 (Box 14)
    - American Public Health Association
      - General, 1964-1965 (Box 15)
      - Committee on Professional Education, 1964-1965 (Box 15)
      - Executive Board, 1964-1965; 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Joint Committee for Post-Commission Action, 1965-1966 (Box 15)
      - Legislation, 1964-1965 (Box 15)
    - Committees
      - General, 1964-1965 (Box 15)
      - Advisory Committee on Academic Rank (nee Promotions), 1964-1965 (Box 15)
      - Assembly, 1964 (Box 15)
      - Continued Education and Community Relations, 1964-1965; 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Executive, 1964-1965 (Box 15)
      - Faculty Meetings, 1964-1965 (Box 15)
      - Instruction, 1964-1965; 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Library, 1964 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence
      - 1964-1965, 12 folders (Box 15)
    - Departments/Divisions
      - Biostatistics (F. Moore), 1964-1965 (Box 16)
      - Bureau of Public Health Economics (S. Axelrod), 1964 (Box 16)
        (see Medical Care Organization in 1965)
      - Community Health (V. Getting), 1964-1965
        - Public Health Nursing (E. McNeil), 1964 (Box 16)
      - Environmental Health (C. Velz), 1964-1965 (Box 16)
      - Epidemiology (T. Francis), 1964-1965
        - Research Center in Diseases of the Heart, 1964-1965 (Box 16)
      - Health Development (R. Bowman, M. Rugen, D. Smith, and C. Woodruff), 1964-1965; 4 folders (Box 16)
      - Industrial Health (H. Magnuson), 1964-1965 (Box 16)
      - Medical Care Organization (S. Axelrod), 1965 (Box 16)
  - Annual Files, 1966
    - Administration
      - General, 1966 (Box 16)
      - Annual Reports, 1964-1965 (Box 16)
      - Library, 1966 (Box 16)
      - Memoranda (department heads), 1966 (Box 16)
      - Memoranda (faculty), 1965-1966 (Box 16)
      - Photographs, 1966 (Box 16)
      - Students, 1966 (Box 16)
    - American Public Health Association
      - Annual meeting (San Francisco), 1966 (Box 16)
      - Committee on Professional Education, 1966 (Box 16)
      - Executive Board, 1966; 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Legislation, 1966 (Box 16)
    - Committees
      - Ad hoc Committee on the 25th Anniversary of the School of Public Health, 1964-1966 (Box 16)
      - Advisory Committee on Academic Rank, 1965-1966 (Box 16)
      - Continued Education and Community Relations, 1965-1966 (Box 16)
      - Executive, 1966 (Box 16)
      - Faculty Meetings, 1966 (Box 16)
      - Instruction, 1966 (Box 16)
      - Scholarship, 1966 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence
      - January-June, 1966, 3 folders (Box 16)
      - July-December, 1966, 3 folders (Box 17)
    - Departments/Divisions
      - Biostatistics (F. Moore), 1966 (Box 17)
      - Community Health (V. Getting), 1966
        - Public Health Nursing (E. McNeil), 1966 (Box 17)
      - Environmental Health (C. Velz), 1966 (Box 17)
      - Epidemiology (T. Francis), 1966
        - Research Center for Diseases of the Heart (Box 17)
      - Health Development (R. Bowman, M. Rugen, and E. Tiboni), 1966; 3 folders (Box 17)
      - Industrial Health (H. Magnuson), 1965-1966 (Box 17)
      - Medical Care Organization (S. Axelrod), 1966 (Box 17)
      - Population Planning Center (L. Corsa), 1966 (Box 17)
  - Annual Files, 1967
    - Administration
      - General, 1967 (Box 17)
      - Annual Reports, 1966-1967 (Box 17)